Tariq Mansour Senior Software engineer

Current Address: Kurdistan, Erbil, Ankawa

Mobile No: (+964)7511870613

Email: tariqahman@gmail.com / tariq.1991@live.com

Personal Profile

Nationality: Palestinian-Syrian with accommodation in Erbil Kurdistan.

Place and date of birth: Damascus, 26/05/1991

Languages: Arabic (native), English (IELTS certified with score 7.0), French

(intermediate) and German (intermediate).

Summary of Skills

A confident and reliable software engineer with extensive practical experience of analyzing, designing, integrating and developing systems. As well as an experienced team leader with supervision, team building and project management experience who has an eye for detail and able to multi-task under pressure. An excellent communicator, can relate well with people at all levels and has the flexibility of working well as part of a team and on my own.

Experience

- March/2021-present : Automation Architect at Huawei Erbil/Iraq
 - Analyze the needed requirements from the telecom companies on Huawei Automation system.
 - Develop new automation workflows to automate internal processes at telecom companies.
 - Modify and tune existing automation workflows to fulfill telecom companies requirements.
 - Prepare the needed documents for each task such as SRS,UAT,...etc.
 - Train the clients on the system in online and onsite sessions.
 - Test the system with client and solve the reported bugs with development team

Main Achievements

- Automate network monitoring processes
 - Description: now the network monitoring process in one of major telecom companies is fully automated achieve minimum human intervention and traceability for all actions on the field and back office.
 - Used technologies: JavaScript, SQL.
- August/2020-present : Software BSS Architect at Huawei Erbil/Iraq
 - Analyze the needed requirements from the telecom companies on billing and charging system.
 - Support telecom companies in applying their processes and requirements on billing and charging system.
 - Apply health checks, rectifications, acceptance tests,...etc. on billing and charging system.

• Setup the appropriate design for billing and charging system integration with other network elements.

Main Achievements

- DR operation
 - Description: apply the most complicated operation which is swap the billing and charging system to DR site with minimum impact and service outage.
 - Used technologies: Linux, Oracle, Java.
- March/2020-August/2020: Technical project manager at Maliatec sales automation company Erbil/Iraq
 - Analyze the needed requirements from the clients who need to automate their sales workflow to scope the project.
 - Develop a scheduler and time plan for each project with its tasks and apply the needed follow up.
 - Prepare the needed documents for each task such as SRS,UAT,...etc.
 - Implement and test the system on client server with all needed reports, processes, tunings,...etc.
 - Train the clients on the system in online and onsite sessions.
 - Test the system with client and solve the reported bugs with development team.

Main Achievements

- o Two FMCJ companies
 - Description: two of the bigest FMCJ companies in Erbil were automated using Maliatec sales automation system in a timely manner and best results.
 - Used skills : Project management skills
 - Used technologies : ASP.net, SQL.
- March/2017-December/2019: System integration head of section at Syriatel telecommunication company Damascus/Syria:
 - Set in-house systems design and lead the team and participate in gathering requirements, analyzing and developing these systems.
 - Study and analyze all readymade systems to be replaced with in-house systems.
 - Review third party systems requirements and set the needed technical requirements and integrations.
 - Make sure to deliver Syriatel offers, services and in-house developed systems on time.
 - Plan, set timeframes, and manage all available resources in the best way to achieve the best outcome.
 - Practice supervision duties which are interview and recruit new employees, follow up, delegation, leadership, training, ..etc.

Main Achievements

- Syriatel Retail System
 - Description: analyze, design and develop Syriatel Retail System which is used by POSs and authorized shops using web or mobile application to serve Syriatel customers to buy new line, pay their invoices, install service, change SIM, ...etc.
 - Used technologies : ASP MVC, Android, Java, PL/SQL.

- E-Wallet system
 - Description: set the design, workflow and processes for E-Wallet system and analyze the proposed third party systems after making RFP which fulfills the requirements and Central Bank regulations.
- January/2015- March/2017: integration specialist at Syriatel telecommunication company Damascus/Syria:
 - Develop systems that need integration with Syriatel core systems which are billing system, charging system and e-recharge system.
 - Analyze, design, implement, test and deploy new services.
 - Generate reports, solve complaints, perform daily checks, develop monitoring tools and set up alarms.
 - Integrate Syriatel channels (USSD, IVR, SMS, Web, Mobile, Kiosk, ...etc.) or external parties (Bank, providers,...) with Syriatel core systems which are billing system, charging system and e-recharge system.

Main Achievements

- o E-Recharge system
 - Description: analyze, design and develop Syriatel erecharge system which allows Syriatel customers to recharge their lines online through different channels (USSD, Website, Web service).
 - Used Technologies : ASP.net, WCF, Java, PL/SQL.
- Online charging system
 - Description: integrate Syriatel Huwaei OCS system with different user channels and systems to manage customers lines, profiles, offers,...etc.
 - Used Technologies: Java, XML, PL/SQL.
- Freelance
 - February/2020-March/2020: Mobile Developer at Creatto business solution company – Erbil/Iraq

Main Achievements

- Qirtasiye
 - Description: analyze, design, develop and publish on Google Play a delivery mobile application to deliver stationary that allows delivery guy to receive and deliver orders on the app with all needed information
 - Used technologies : Flutter, Firebase, PHP, MySQL.
- January/2016-February/2016: Web Developer remotely
 - Main Achievements
 - WeBid
 - Description: analyze, design and develop ecommerce website that allows companies to market their products and for product buyers to search for products and buy them.
 - o Used technologies: PHP, MySQL.

Education

- 2015-present Web Master at Syrian Virtual University;
- 2009-2015 Information Technology Engineering
 - University : Damascus University (FITE)
 - Majority: information systems and software engineering
 - Average: 77.02% (very good)
 - Many academic projects in different fields (web, mobile, database, compiler, graphics,...etc.) using different programming languages (PHP, JSP, SQL, Oracle, ...etc.)

Technical skills

- Programming languages:
 - Advanced: PHP, ASP.net, JSP, Jquery, HMTL, CSS, JavaScript, C#, C#.Net, JAVA, Java form, web service (Soap, Rest and WCF), SQL, MySQL, PL/SQL and ORACLE.
 - Medium: Scripting language (sh and bat), Pascal, Delphi, C++,
 C++.Net, ASP MVC, Flutter and Oracle ADF.
 - Basic : Angular, Android and ASP core.
- Platforms: Windows and Linux.

Awards and Certificates

- Huawei Certification in Cloud Computing (Aug, 2021);
- Huawei Certification in Python (June, 2021);
- Huawei Certification in Big data (Sep, 2020);
- Angular 5 in Arabic Academic for e-business (April 2018);
- Leadership and team management (March, 2018);
- MVC in Arabic Academic for e-business (June, 2016);
- Effective ways to solve problems course (February, 2016);
- Web Programming And Development (HTML, CSS, JavaScript, JQuery and PHP) at CCIT (January, 2013);
- Web design (Adobe Photoshop, Flash Professional and Dreamweaver) at CCIT (January,2012);
- C++, Delphi, OPEN GL course at Alnukhbe Center (2010-2011);
- Chairman award for replacing 3rd party e-recharge system with in-house developed system;
- Thank you awards for completing many projects in Syriatel like Re-pricing, OCS, Self-Service, Competition, ...etc.